<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Emmertons marriage with Mrs. Bridget Hyde considered wherein is discoursed the rights and nature of marriage, what authority the Curia Christianitatis hath in matrimonial causes at this day, the levitical degrees, the bounds of a legal marriage, and the reasons thereof, and that now matrimonial causes are determinable by virtue of the statute of H. 8. by the judges of common law : in a letter from a gentleman in the country to one of the commissioners delegates in that cause, desiring his opinion therein.</title>
            <author>Hunt, Thomas, 1627?-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15660</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11849549</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11849549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49899</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45196)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49899)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 498:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Emmertons marriage with Mrs. Bridget Hyde considered wherein is discoursed the rights and nature of marriage, what authority the Curia Christianitatis hath in matrimonial causes at this day, the levitical degrees, the bounds of a legal marriage, and the reasons thereof, and that now matrimonial causes are determinable by virtue of the statute of H. 8. by the judges of common law : in a letter from a gentleman in the country to one of the commissioners delegates in that cause, desiring his opinion therein.</title>
                  <author>Hunt, Thomas, 1627?-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Author and published by Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Matrimonial actions --  England.</term>
               <term>Marriage law --  England.</term>
               <term>Marriage (Canon law)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49899:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49899:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>EMMERTONS</hi> MARRIAGE WITH Mrs. <hi>BRIDGET HYDE</hi> CONSIDERED.</p>
            <p>Wherein is diſcourſed the Rights and Nature of Marriage.</p>
            <p>What Authority the <hi>Curia Chriſtianitatis</hi> hath in Matrimonial Cauſes at this day.</p>
            <p>The Levitical Degrees, the Bounds of a Legal Marriage, and the Reaſons thereof.</p>
            <p>And that now Matrimonial Cauſes are determinable by Virtue of the Statute of <hi>H.</hi> 8. by the Judges of Common Law.</p>
            <p>In a Letter from a Gentleman in the Country to one of the Commiſſioners Delegates in that Cauſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring his Opinion therein.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <bibl>Marc. Antonin.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Authour, and Publiſhed by <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49899:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49899:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>EMMERTON's</hi> MARRIAGE WITH Mrs. <hi>BRIDGET HYDE</hi> CONSIDERED.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received your Letter, wherein you were pleaſed to conſult me, and to deſire my thoughts how a Judge in the Cauſe of Mr. <hi>Emmerton</hi>'s Marriage to Mrs. <hi>Bridget Hyde</hi> now depending, before the Commiſſioners of Delegates, ought to guide himſelf. And what Opinion I have of the Authority of ſuch Commiſſioners: And to reſolve you how Matrimonial Cauſes came to be thus ſplit and the ſame cauſe in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral reſpects of ſeveral Conuſance. The Queſtion of Right Cognoſcible in the <hi>Curia Chriſtianitatis;</hi> But the Queſtion of Fact in our Common Law Courts: How this inconvenience and irregularity came about, and whether it be not remedyed by the Stat. of <hi>H.</hi> 8. which prohibits Marriages to be Impeached that are contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Perſons not within the Levitical degrees of Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. By that Statute the Laws of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> is become a Statute Law of <hi>England;</hi> and the interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Church her Authority, in defining within
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49899:3"/>
what degrees Marriages can be lawfully made, are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged. The Canons of the Church have always given the Rule to all Chriſtendome in theſe Matters, Matrimonial Cauſes are conducted every where by the Canon Law where it is not controld by the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Law of the State. As the Civil Law doth govern in moſt Countries, in all Caſes where no mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicipal Laws or local Cuſtoms do intervene: what the Roman Civil Law hath Eſtabliſh'd, is not the meaſure of Matrimonial Cauſes, but the Canon Law or Councels of the Church, which is not ſo in any other Cauſes refer'd by our Conſtitutions to the Civil Law Courts.</p>
            <p>You likewiſe deſire my Opinion about the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal degrees, and for what reaſon Marriages within theſe degrees are forbidden, and whether we ought to ſtand within the Letter of that Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the prohibited inſtances, and not take Caſes under aparity of Reaſon to be likewiſe prohibited: Whether our Common Law Courts are not competent to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and Interpret a Chapter of <hi>Leveticus</hi> and a Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> as well as any other Writing, or as our own Statute Laws. And conſequently the Authority of the Church precluded in judging any longer about the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of Marriages in reſpect of the degrees of Kindred: which you think was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon that the Church interpoſed in Matrimonial Cauſes: which were certainly before the Statute of <hi>H.</hi> 8. within their Province. And that duly, for that they had been from the firſt publiſhing of our Religion, accounted of a Religious conſideration, and were declar'd by the Laws, and the Spirit, and Purity of our Religion; and thoſe matters were rightly and fitly conducted by the guides of our Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49899:3"/>Sir, as ſoon as I read your Commands, I applyed my ſelf, all other matters, but neceſſary avocations neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to give you ſuch a return as I could, not conſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my own great inſufficiency to reſolutions in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch high moment, but conſidering, that you deſired what I could, not, what I could not ſay in the matter. But in what I fall ſhort of your expectation, you muſt impute it to the very ſhort time you allotted me, a peremptary day for this cauſe being very near, and what I ſhall after that time offer, may be like ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice adminiſtered to a departing man.</p>
            <p>But that which did moſt diſcourage me in this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, was want of particular notice of the Cauſe, you having ſupply'd to me but ſome Generals, and given me onely the complexion of the Cauſe, and not given it me, repreſented in all its lineaments and parts, nor furniſhed me any of thoſe niceties that have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed the Cauſe, nor thoſe Arts which have given it all this delay; by which the iniquity of a pretence may be diſcerned, and the zeal of a Righteous man may be provok'd and excited. But tho you have not troubled your ſelf with a prolix account of thoſe matters for the ſparing my trouble, I am pleaſed that you are not without a juſt reſentment of them, and they will be duly conſidered by you when you come to form your Judgment, for I underſtand by you that you were not at the laſt Seſſion in this Cauſe, being deteined by very weighty affairs of your own, and preſuming (as you ſay) that you could not imagine, that a Cauſe of that clearneſs, a Matrimonial Cauſe, a Cauſe of any other to be highly favour'd, a Cauſe that would not ſuffer any longer delay. The miſcheifs and the ſin of thoſe delays becoming every day more crying and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49899:4"/>
could not but find a ready Sentence from worthy men that are touch'd with a ſence of Juſtice, and have any zeal for the Rights of Marriage, the happieſt and beſt Inſtitution in the World, and the moſt Sacred and inviolate Faith of the Matrimonial Contract,</p>
            <p>For, Sir, moſt true it is, that many and great are the advantages to mankind, that proceed from the ſtate of Marriages (that is to ſay) a propagation of our kind, honeſt and well-becoming the Dignity of our Nature, a more effective and buſie care of two Parents in Educating our Children, by which the better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving our kind is provided for.</p>
            <p>This State ſecures to every Child a Father, as it doth appropriate the Child to the Husband, ſo that we are entertained alſo with the love of our Children, as well as the Woman who would otherwiſe enjoy a pleaſure, of which we could hardly ever partake.</p>
            <p>The labours and cares of our life are encouraged, ſuſteined, and rewarded by the love of our Iſſue and Poſterities, and they enjoy the Riches, and Honours, and Rewards of their Fathers Wiſdom and Virtue, which would otherwiſe determine into the firſt acquirer, return to the <hi>fiſcus,</hi> or without ſatisfaction, be beſtowed upon a leſs beloved Stranger. The worthy and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ambition conſequently of performing worthy Actions, and rendring our ſelves uſeful to the publick, would ceaſe and languiſh, the publick good be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected, and Kingdoms and Commonwealths diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, and we become again as Savage as the Beaſts themſelves, unguarded and without the comforts or Ornaments of humane life.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49899:4"/>
               <hi>Cecrops</hi> from his Inſtitution of Marriage at <hi>Athens</hi> is honor'd with the Title of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by this Inſtitution we all become <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and know our Fathers, Without Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, our great men, who undervalue and diſgrace it, had found themſelves among the heard, and for ever there had continued and never enjoy'd the honours of their Anceſtors, from whom they vilely degenerate.</p>
            <p>But beſides the advantages that we derive from this State of Marriage to our whole kind in the better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for the Improvement of humane Nature, and the accommodations of life: it doth immediately confer an honour and dignity upon our nature, when we do thoſe Acts that are common to us with the Beaſts, we do not in this State perform them brutally. They are the effects rather of Friendſhip than Luſt, and a kind of Chaſtity belongs truly to theſe Amours.</p>
            <p>By the Encloſure of this State we have acquired Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty to our Nature; Thereby the very Appetites of Nature are duly retrench'd and brought into Rule: and this by Example becomes a Bridle and Reſtraint to the Younger Sort, before they come under the guidance of Reaſon and Underſtanding, and directs the Natural Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to take care of their Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>Whilſt we ſtand to the Obligations that this State puts us under, we are free from the Incontinency of a Vagabond Luſt, which is infinite, unbounded and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable, it befools as many as it poſſeſſeth, and makes them become Vain, and light to Contempt, utterly uſeleſs to any Manly purpoſes, betrays them to Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Sloath, and an incurable Voluptuouſneſs, leaves them without Soul, and without Vertue, ſinks them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a low and Brutal Life, and leaves them without fear
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49899:5"/>
of God, or regard to Men, and makes them the vileſt Knaves, gives them a Languiſhing and Spiritleſs Health, and often precipitates them into a naſty and ſqualid Old Age, and a haſty Death, they are always perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with contempt and diſhonour whilſt they live, and their Children Inherit their Shame, fore that they are Sinners againſt the Laws of Modeſty and Decency, which this State hath Introduced, and Diſhonour Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, and Violate that Natural Pudor, by this State directed and fortified; which ſo directed, the Moraliſts call <hi>Pudicitia,</hi> which once loſt is irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <q>Laeſa pudicitia eſt nulla reparabilis arte.</q>
            <p>I had not made this Digreſſion, but that I fear, The Contempt that this Licentious Age hath brought upon Marriage, gives occaſion to leſs conſidering Men to trifle with Matrimonial Cauſes, but the miſchiefs that are conſequent upon the contempt of Marriage, have ſufficiently Reveng'd the Indignities done to that State, and Vindicated its Honour, <hi>viz.</hi> Spurious and Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Broods, as vile in their Manners, as they are vilely Got, and worſe Bred. And hence it is that the greateſt Families often laſt not longer then the ſingle Life of a Virtuous Man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49899:5"/>
               <hi>Conjugium rem Eſse vere ſaeram non humanitùs ſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitùs repertam magno conſenſu gentes crediderunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Grotius.</hi> And they who truly conſider the matter muſt thus conclude.</p>
            <p>Marriages agreeably have been every where hollowed with holy Rites, the Offices of Religion, and the Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Prieſts: it being a State directed to, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable (if bleſſed by God) of producing, and miniſtring to many ineſtimable Benefits to Mankind; Marriages have been in all Ages every where celebrated with feſtival Joy and Mirth, and every Man hath a Congratulation for the new married Couple; as if it did import ſome common and univerſal Good: Many priviledges have been granted to this Eſtate to invite and encourage it, it hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times been made neceſſary and enjoyn'd by Laws. The <hi>Jews</hi> take themſelves oblidg'd to marry and that early too, and did allow only a temporary Diſpenſation for publick good to men that might in that interim of time make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very uſeful to the publick. The Entry into that State made eaſy and expedite diſcharging Conditions, that lay any Reſtraint upon our Liberty of Choice where we are capable of chooſing.</p>
            <p>The Government hath provided Formula's for this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant contract, that the contractors may not be deceived in their intention for want of words ſignificant to that purpoſe, and operative of that contract, but in theſe their Proviſions they have not inſerted any <hi>verba irrtiantia</hi> and made the Marriage void, if the words uſed by the contractors do conclude to that contract, though they do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49899:6"/>
depart from the Form &amp; Ceremony preſcribed, and kindly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Government, in favor of that ſtate Governments enjoyn publick Marriages, that they may be better atteſted, and that that ſacred contract be not fruſtrated and defraud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but they do not annul clandeſtine Marriages. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a greater violence was never at any time done to Nature, nor any abſurdity greater enacted by the infamous Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> than that Councels declaring clandeſtine Marriages to be null and void. The forms of eſpouſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> were eaſy, in few words obvious, no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Form enjoyn'd. Some of them I will recite out of <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monides, Ecce tu mihi es per hoc diſponſata, Ecce tu mihi tum hoc es in Vxorem, mea es, es mea accepta, es in poteſtate meâ,</hi> but the more common Form was, <hi>En diſponſata mihi es hac re ſecundum ritum Maſis &amp; Iſraelis.</hi> He alſo relates the Law to be thus <hi>(Viz) Vir poteſt Mulierem deſponſare quîvis Linguâ, quam ipſa intelligat modo verbis vtatur ſignificationem talem, ut modo dictum, habentibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when Marriages were to be diſſolv'd by Divorces, in favor of marriages, and in disfavor of Divorces rather permitted as uſed amongſt them, than allowed or appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. It was required, that there ſhould be a Bill of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce, and in this they require abundance of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and Form as well about the writing of it, as the delivering to make it difficult, and unfeaſible or very eaſily defeated, that ſo upon the abatement of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands diſpleaſure, the marriage may be redintegrated by ſome matter of Exception to the Bill of Divorce; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which there were a Number of Queſtions even to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49899:6"/>
the Ink and Pen, wherewith it was written the number of the lines, and the Figure of the Letters.</p>
            <p>A precontract or inchoat Marriage is indiſſoluble, tho in other Affairs the Rule of Law, which almoſt univerſally obtains, is <hi>Nihil actum videtur quam diu aliquid ſupereſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum.</hi> But ſuch effect this Precontract hath, that it diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and reſcinds any ſubſequent Marriage, tho Children are born in the after Marriage, and tho the Perſon married to the Precontractor was neſcient of the Precontract and no <hi>Dolus malus</hi> imputable to the Perſon ſo married.</p>
            <p>The matrimonial contract being founded in Nature, and made ſacred by Divine inſtitution, being neceſſary to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and producing the greateſt Benefits, becomes thereby the more ſacred and inviolable, and can therefore be more early made and agreed, and for this reaſon the Perſons are rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned competent to make a valid marriage at ſuch an age, at which they cannot oblige themſelves with effect in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affair or concernment, nay then when they can ſcarce by any Act render themſelves criminal, and are ſcarce <hi>Pilii praecepti</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> call them. The mans conſent at 14. and the Womans conſent at 12 is unalterable, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable, for that beſides at theſe Ages they can make Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and chuſe their Companions, and can ſeparate out of many ſome one with whom they are more particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, and pleaſed with a propenſeneſs of affection, and entertain one an other with a pure and undeſigning love, and complacency, not at all ſullied with the Paſſion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence; and Marriages, that are made upon ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements under the guidance and allowance of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49899:7"/>
and Tutors, if all things elſe are agreeable, are moſt apt to prove the moſt chaſt, happy and undefiled Marriages. The Law is wiſe and good, that allows them the inducement upon which it is grounded is reaſonable, and the Law it ſelf commendable. But however Law it is, and to that as to the meaſure of right, we muſt determine our ſelves, and conform our Conſciences. A preſent ſufficiency to Acts of Venery is no neceſſary requiſit to the making of that Contract rate and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>firm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>Neither is the performing of them neceſſary, in any degree, to the making the matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial contract compleat: by that contract, indeed the Man and Woman reſpectively have a right to each other; but no right can be created by the Exerciſe of that right. I have often obſerved with great pleaſure the Marks of Divinity in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and in the inſtitutions of that Common-wealth, but in nothing more then in the cleanneſs of that Law, of which I ſhall remark one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the preſent purpoſe; there was amongſt them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Eſpouſals before they proceeded to marriage, which could not be reſcinded any other way, but as marriages were undone; and that which was adultery in the woman after marriage, was accounted, and puniſh'd as adultery after the Eſpouſals, and before the marriage, but infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous it was to contract thoſe Eſpouſals <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu, as it is amongſt us to marry upon the firſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view.</p>
            <p>This interim between Eſpouſals and Marriage, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for conciliating a Friendſhip between the Eſpouſed Perſons ſuch a love, that might ſupport the happineſs of that conjugal Eſtate, and laſt when the fervors of luſt were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49899:7"/>
abated: very neceſſary to that ſalacious People, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch proviſion would have had greater pleaſure <hi>in matrimonio quam marito nuptiis quam in nuptâ,</hi> and the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage State muſt then needs have been very tranſitory, when they had the liberty amongſt them of divorcing. And this Law, and practiſe <hi>Lycurgus</hi> tranſcribed for the Common-wealth of <hi>Sparta;</hi> So little is the buſineſs of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubitus</hi> to be had in Conſideration by the Virtuous and wiſe conſiderers of what is neceſſary and convenient to the making the State of Marriage happy, and virtuous and bleſſed with a laſting Friendſhip; as alſo what is preciſely requiſite to the making a Marriage.</p>
            <p>So great aſſurance this contract gives us, and ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation all Law-givers give to the faith of marriage for the quieting of Jealouſy and Caprices, and curious En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirys of ſuſpicious Men, and for the peace of Familys, and for the encouraging that State, and to diſtinguiſh it from a looſe Concubinat. That the Husband is preſum'd to be Father of the Children, when he cohabits with his Wife, and will not ſuffer the legitimacy of a Child born in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to be litigated, and diſputed: And indeed it cannot be diſputed, for filiation cannot be prov'd or diſprov'd, and no Judicature ever allowed any allegation, to ſuch purpoſe an allegation of this nature, is not more injurious to the Perſon to whom it is objected, then it is againſt the ſacred rights and priviledg, that in all ages have been conſtantly acknowledged, zealouſly aſſerted neceſſarily to reſult from the matrimonial State. It is no leſs iniquity to form his Judgment by any reſpect to ſuch ſuggeſtion, whenceſoever it comes, or to his own ſurmiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49899:8"/>The matrimonial contract between competent Perſons canot be really prejudiced, by any miſtake in Judgment, or by any Laws whatſoever of human legiſlation in derogation thereof. The rights that reſult from marriage differs in this, from all other rights whatſoever, this may ſeem ſtrang; But for this, I have the Authority of an univerſal conſent of the Drs. of <hi>Canon,</hi> and civil Law, who all tell us <hi>That</hi> a ſentence againſt a marriage, doth not <hi>tranſire in rem judicatam;</hi> whatſoever can be ſubmitted to judicatures, and is under the Government of Laws, the right of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſubmitted, is ſuch as the Judgment of the Court of the laſt reſort makes it, and whether the Judgment be right or wrong according to the natural reaſon of right Juſtice, it matters not. And if the defendant before had a right, the right to the things in pretence, by the Judment for the Plantiff, ceaſes to be the Defendants, right any longer, and can be no longer poſſeſſed without a publick injuſtice; all thoſe things, that are in our power to give or alien, may be thus forfeited to the conſtitution of the Government, under which we are and of ſuch cauſes it is true.</p>
            <q>Praetor jus dicit quum iniquum decernit.</q>
            <p>But in all matters wherein any Law of God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed really, or in general opinion, in matters, that are bound upon us by an Oath, or a religious Vow in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lawful, whereby we have a Conſcience towards God, no human Authority can make us ſafe, if we depart from the rule of our own Conſcience. Decrees of Councels, and Laws of Princes cannot change a Mans underſtanding, neither can ſentences in matters of this nature take the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49899:8"/>
in Execution, and Execute themſelves by changing the mind, and enforcing a belief upon the underſtanding, and for this reaſon our <hi>Canoniſts</hi> and <hi>Civilians</hi> conclude, that matrimonial cauſes do not <hi>tranſire in rem judicatam.</hi> They can puniſh and afflict the Perſon, diſgrace the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages upon ſtrong Preſumptions in fact againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended marriage, or for that marriages are made otherwiſe than as <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Canons,</hi> for preventing inconveniences have directed. But they who know the truth of the fact, and are under the obligation of a contract made in purſuant of Gods inſtitution, and not contrary to any injunction of his appointment, muſt as much as in them lyeth, and as is poſſible for them, perform, fulfil and obſerve it, and their Conſciences are onerated with it everlaſtingly, and cannot be diſcharged by any nullity Sentence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Such Laws as are made arbitrarily for the reſtraining of the liberty of marriages permitted, or not prohibited in firſt nature; If they do uſe only prohibiting words, and not add expreſs words, that a marriage ſo made ſhall be null and void, a marriage prohibited is not therefore null and void; for though it may be very convenient to make further a reſtraint in the matter of marriages, than Nature peremptorily enjoyns (and in ſuch Laws the rule holds, <hi>Quod fieri non debet factum valet</hi> obtains.) Tho not further then reaſon of Decence, and General convenience doth perſwade, which is always the rule to refined under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and where there is a perfect virtue.</p>
            <p>Yet human Laws which command, and not perſwade are never interpreted to onerate the Conſcience, nor are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49899:9"/>
intended beyond the expreſs letter thereof, to tye men to the neceſſity of performing acts of virtue, which ceaſe to be ſo if done by command, and not by a prompt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity and eaſy inclination. The formal reaſon of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue conſiſteth in being voluntary, and free, that it be not done of conſtraint, but of a ready mind, no man can be charitable or grateful in any inſtance, if he be ſo by the compulſion, and conſtraint of a Law; neither can he be counted chaſt, valiant or patient, if he be not ſo in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the inward love, and Complacency, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction he takes in comporting with the Rules of the like Virtues. It is no Exception againſt the legal validity of any act, that it is not altogether without fault, and the moſt commendable.</p>
            <p>The Lawes of nature themſelves have different con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, Acts of vitue in the firſt degree are enjoyn'd by the Law of Nature. <hi>(viz.)</hi> where the not performing them tenders the man vitious and miſchievous, and our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for theſe omiſſions by ſharp convictions, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences againſt our ſelves, binds us over to the expectation of dreadful puniſhments to be inflicted upon us at the great Tribunal. But we are invited to great and noble acts of virtue, by the gloriations and applauſes of our conſciences, which are the anticipations of that Honor and Glory, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from God. To ſuch Acts, we do not find our ſelves compelled or urg'd by fear, but invited to them by the worthineſs of the Acts themſelves, and the Honor that attends them, and the comfortable expectation of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Immortality; But beſides the neceſſary firſt Acts of Virtue, which is a little elſe then not being wicked to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49899:9"/>
which we are bound by fear of puniſhment, and the free and voluntary Acts of a noble virtue, to which we are invited by increas'd rewards; which are threatned and promiſed, and in ſome ſort performed and executed in, and by our own Conſciences.</p>
            <p>There are a ſort of Laws of preciſe decency, which our Conſciences oblidge us to obſerve; for our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in whatever it dictates, declares the Law of Nature to us, and the not obſerving theſe matters of decence af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects us with ſome ſhame, and the obſerving of them renders us honeſt, to our ſelves the neglect of them is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> than <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the greateſt puniſhment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in Nature is bluſhing, and the greateſt reward of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them is, that we do not fall into a Diſeſteem of our ſelves, and a dejection of mind. And in conformity to the rule of our conſcience by civil Government, matters of inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency (when prohibited by Law) are only noted with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny wickedneſs is puniſhed, and virtue is rewarded. The procedure of our conſciences hath governed human Laws, as well as it inſtructs us how God will proceed with us; by which we become inexcuſable.</p>
            <q>Pub. Mim. Grave eſt judicium vbi nullum eſt praejudicium.</q>
            <p>But all Acts, that are prohibited in nature as undecent, and inconvenient are not therefore null and void, for that the indecency may lye in the very Act, and not in the effects, that that Act produceth, and the inconveniencies, that follow the reſcinding of the act may be greater than the indecence, and inconvenience of the act it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49899:10"/>That which I mean to ſay is, that the doing a thing undecently, to which I have a Competent authority doth not therefore want effect; Laws prohibitory of ſuch Acts. If they do not irritate as well as prohibit, leave ſuch Acts when prohibited in force, much rather have they effect when there is no ſuch prohibitory Law, and therefore the conſideration, that a thing is not unqueſtionably well ought to have no direction in a Judicial ſentence, for mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Act done by a competent Power null and void. A Sin in nature is much, rather to be avoided than a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, which ſeems to be forbidden at moſt by the rules of decence, and the preciſe meaſure of conveniency.</p>
            <p>In matrimonial cauſes, nothing is to be favor'd but the marriage it ſelf, no quality is conſiderable in the Perſons contracting marriage, but that which give them capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to make the contract: Whether the Perſons be of the ſame, or of different Religions of a true or falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makes no matter: In caſe of a Marriage, between a Chriſtian woman, with a Pagan or Jew if any thing can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach the Marriage, its becauſe they do not contract for a marriage according to the Chriſtian Law, but under the Liberty of an arbitrary Divorce, and Polygamy which is not agreeable to the inſtitutions of our Saviour. But if a Jew, Pagan or Mahometan received the Chriſtian Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, but yeſterday he is a better Chriſtian than if he had been baptiſed in his Cradle for that he was ſo lately baptiſed if he be ſincere in his profeſſion, which none but God can know, but Man ought to preſume. The proof of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is to be favor'd by the Judges in matrimonial cauſes: Where the probabilitys on either ſide, for or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the marriage are equal. The danger of Sin of an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49899:10"/>
unpardonable Sin which may be occaſion'd by a ſentence againſt the marriage, ought to determine for the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: The conſideration of this, ought to be put into the Ballance of Judgment in ſuch caſes, and make the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>In ſuch caſes the evil Fear'd is greater than the Good, that can accrue to the Perſon, that pretends to diſſolve the marriage, which is only the Liberty of another choice. In Charity therefore the Judgment, ought to prevent the greater evil by recluding the occaſion of it, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in favour of the pretended marriage, which is inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſafe; but ſo probably prov'd. Beſides that the incurring the probability of occaſioning this Evil cannot be juſtified by the Freedom they deſign her. It is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the favor, that is due and allowed to the marriage contract, that it ſhould be expoſed to all the Artifices of Wit, and Cavillations of Law, that the Wit of Men can invent to leſſon the credibility of the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony produced in its Confirmation. By a ſingle Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of putting the marriage under an ill Name, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it a Clandeſtine marriage with an accent of cenſure they make all the Witneſſes, that are proper to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy ſuch a Contract, and are to be preſent, if any other, for that bad Name ſake <hi>ſuſpectae fidei,</hi> and incompetent Witneſſes. Clandeſtinity is the word of reproach; which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rys with it no fault but a neglect of that ſolemnity, which would have put the matter out of all diſpute; this is the diſparaging Name they affix with art to this Marriage. But an innocent and prudent reaſon the caſe it ſelf gives, and aſſigns for that Circumſtance of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49899:11"/>
Marriage; and that which tells us why a thing is ſo, and ſo done, and in ſuch manner, contributes to the proof that the thing was really done, when performed in that form and manner. If the marriage had been celebrated in the Church it had been leſs credible, the Mothers conſent would have been leſs credited, and ſhe it may be dare not have own'd it to her defeated Husband. The Clerk that marry'd (which is to be complained of) was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly corrupted by threats, and promiſes to deny the marriage: Under theſe temptations he is a notorious falſary in what he thus ſaith to avoid the marriage, and yet what he ſaith under theſe circumſtances in affirmation of the Marriage, is rejected as not credible, upon this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral rule, <hi>falſus in vno falſus in omnibus;</hi> when there can be no greater Evidence in the World of the reality and truth of any matter, then violent and lend endeavors to have it disbelieve: Except it be the teſtimony of the Man himſelf, thus practis'd with, on the behalf of that matter thus endeavored to be ſuppreſſed. A clearer Teſtimony was never given to our Saviour of his Divinity then when he was acknowledged by the Devil, the Father of Lyes to be the Son of God.</p>
            <p>But after all this the terms of marriages are made yet harder by the nature, and conſtitution, as generally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, of our Judicatures, that are to judge in matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Cauſes, which if legally ſuch as it is generally tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to be; we ſhall continue unhappy in this matter until we have a Law for our redreſs therein. But the grievance is ſo great, and the contrivance therein ſo little commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable for the Honor of our Nation, that I ſhall offer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49899:11"/>
ſome Reaſons to your better conſideration, to prove that the Eccleſiaſtical Courts have at this time no Judgment in matrimonial Cauſes; but that the right as well as the fact of marriages; are cognoſcible only in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law-Courts. At preſent the fact of a marriage is try'd, and judged in our common Law-Courts. The right of a marriage is litigated in the Eccleſiaſtical Court: Thus the queſtion of right, and the queſtion of fact, which are inſeparable in true Judgment are divided. After the common Law hath enquired into the truth of the Marriage, the Eccleſiaſtical Courts upon a pretence of having the Judgment in the Queſtion of Right, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the marriage be lawfully made, they proceed to fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſify the Verdicts and Judgments in our commen Law-Courts, and to hold Plea whether the Marriage was <hi>de facto</hi> made or no, which is all the matter in Judgment in that Court, after it was ſetled in its proper Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And ſo we have two thwarting Judicatures that are not ſubordinat, and yet this is not all whilſt the matter hath been clear'd on Mr. <hi>Emmertons</hi> behalf in the Court of comon Law, and conſequently he ought to have all the rights of a Husband, poſſeſſion of his wifes Lands, and of her perſon: The Chancery interpoſeth, that hath no manner of Cognizance in the Cauſe neither of the right or fact; and at pleaſure ſequeſters, and diſpoſeth of the Eſtate, and Mr. <hi>Emmerton</hi> muſt content himſelf with Alimony at the allotment of that Court, as if he were the Adultereſs. But it is notorious to the World how dilatory that <hi>Curia Chriſtianitatis</hi> is, which allows ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny appeals and ſo expenſive: That if Mr. <hi>Emmerton</hi> had not marry'd young, he might have been ſuperannuated
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49899:12"/>
for Marriage before the controverſy is ended, and if his Fortune had not been conſiderable, he might have wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bread more than a wife; beſides that they have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Judgment againſt him by the delay, and he hath loſt his Wife except ſhe be reclaim'd by a very improbable repentance. For want of a timely remedy he hath loſt his wife irrecoverably, and it is not in the power of any Court to reſtore her to him, for ſhe hath now alien'd her affections inveteratly. He hath loſt her by the delays of the ſuit, and the countenance therein given to her pretence hath engaged her in great difficultys. A ſuit which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports it ſelf by ſuch means as uſe to feel the power of a Star-chamber: It was accounted a vile Crime amongſt the Jews (and forbidden by the 10th. Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neighbours wife</hi>) to breed and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a diſlike in the Husband towards the Wife, to provoke him to divorce her to the purpoſe to marry her: But this is a far worſe Crime than they were capable of acting; for they have wrought the Wife between diſlike, and enjoyment to divorce and abandon her Husband; a thing monſtrouſly wicked, and very unnatural: And of this Crime the delay, that hath been given to this Cauſe is chargable.</p>
            <p>I am glad it is imputable to things only which have no conſcience, and not to Perſons that have. But this is not all Mr. <hi>Emmerton</hi> knows, he was marry'd to Mrs. <hi>Hide,</hi> and cannot be free from his Marriage, nor marry another without committing Adultery; ſince no Authority can diſſolve the Marriage, and the declaratory Sentence of a Court, that they were not marry'd cannot alter the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49899:12"/>
truth of the caſe, but he is ſtill her Husband, and this all the <hi>Canoniſts</hi> will acknowledge, for that matrimonial Cauſes do not <hi>Tranſire in rem judicatam,</hi> neither can the Marriage be diſſolved by any misbehavior of the wife, a Sentence of Divorce doth not diſſolve the <hi>Vinculum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonii,</hi> and therefore he can much leſs (in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Courts) diſcharg himſelf from the marriage Bond; So that there had need be a very clear Evidence, ſuch as carrys no doubt with it; that can warrant a Nullity ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that is charged with ſuch miſchiefs and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencys. But this cannot be the true State of the Evidence in this Cauſe; ſince notwithſtanding all the Art uſed to leſſen the certainty of the Marriage, and bring it into ſome doubt, the greateſt Authority hath been for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Marriage in all the inſtances of the Cauſes; Nay the beſt managers of the Cauſe on the behalf of Mrs. <hi>Hyde</hi> have apply'd themſelves not ſo much to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate the Evidence as to diſgrace the Perſon of Mr. <hi>Emmerton,</hi> and to provoke thereby an Envy againſt his Right to the Lady which ought not to be endured by any Court; much leſs ought it abuſe, and by as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of a Judge, and corrupt his Judgment.</p>
            <p>But ſuch hardſhips, and inconveniencys as theſe will not be conſidered, and are hard to be prevented in ſuch Commiſſions as are iſſued out in this Cauſe; In which Men are named not for known Wiſdom, and ſufficiency to judge and determine Cauſes in this Nature; but for the greatneſs of their Quality. No Man can act beyond his ſufficiency, and in a doubtful Cauſe, as all Cauſes are doubtful; or with little skill may be made ſo, to Men
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49899:13"/>
that have none. The conſideration of Friendſhip will determine him that cannot govern himſelf by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Cauſe, or will not guide himſelf by the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Men of the beſt Authority and Reputation. It is very hard to be judged by any Man, whoſe Honour doth not depend upon right judging; and where the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in judging may be with more probability imputed to the want of skill, and incompetency, than to wilful Miſtake.</p>
            <p>So that a probable opinion that this cauſe and others of the like nature ought to have their final Judgment at Common Law, will meet with a ready and free conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration I doubt not with our Common Law Judges, ſince they are ſo untowardly and contingently carry'd in theſe Commiſſions, that their proceedings meet with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſſatisfaction, as they are a mighty Gravamen to the Litigants.</p>
            <p>That which I have to ſay in this matter had need be very clear, ſince the notion may ſeem new, and a great prejudice lys againſt it. But it will appear not new be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have done with it, the premiſes from which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it, be all agreed to me; and the Concluſion I make from them will be clearly inferd: It will appear to be as uſeful as true, and therefore I hope have a favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Reception.</p>
            <p>I do not intend to controvert or bring into Queſtion the Right of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, to judge in all Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Offence againſt the Laws of Chaſtity, and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49899:13"/>
of the performance of the conjugal Rights: And to compel the Precontractators to proceed to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and perform the Conjugal dutys. They may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Cauſe <hi>de jactitatione maritagij,</hi> for that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law allows no action of the caſe without ſpecial Damnification, tho in it ſelf it carrys with it a prejudice, and is a very great incumbrance fit to be removed by the Authority of a judicial Sentence. As alſo in a promiſe of a Marriage, where there hath been any Execution of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement to enforce a Marriage: Theſe two laſt Order of Cauſes belongs to them upon the ſame reaſon; as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Covenants in kind, and Examination of Witneſſes in caſe of pretence of title <hi>in perpetuam rei me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriam</hi> belongs to the Court of Chancery, that is as a derelict of the common Law, and for a further Reaſon for that matter may be concern'd, and mov'd in theſe Cauſes which are not ſo becoming our more publick Tryals at common Law. To the Eccleſiaſtical Court belongs all Cauſes of Divorce, and the Puniſhment of inceſtuous Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, where Marriages are void: which our Law ought to judge, and all other ſins of incontinence which are moſt aptly puniſhed with ſhame; a reſtraint of the ſame Nature which God hath planted in our Nature for the bridling thoſe natural Appetits which betray Men into ſuch inordinacys: And in this our Government moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendably follows the Indication of God himſelf in our Nature. I have a great Honor for the Gentlemen of that faculty, and do not, envy any matter of judicature that truly belongs to them; I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a true civilian, that hath the Learning that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to that faculty to be the beſt accompliſhed Man, and of the moſt univerſal Uſefulneſs to the World; and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49899:14"/>
if all Cauſes of Matrimony were aſſigned to be judged only by Men of that Faculty, and not by miſcellaneous and fortuitous Heap of Men which make the Delegates in moſt Cauſes: This Cauſe of Mr. <hi>Emmertons</hi> Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age had not been ſo afflicted and vexed, and prejudiced by Reaſons which publickly to mention, would I fear be accounted a Libel againſt the Government; for the Eminent Drs. of that faculty have acquitted themſelves honorably in the Cauſe, and have given Reputation to the Cauſe of Mr. <hi>Emmerton</hi> under all the diſcountenance, that hath been caſt upon it for little other Reaſon than from the diſparity in his Condition with that of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Litigant. It is not I declare any Exception againſt the Juſtice of the civil Law-Courts, or againſt their Law, that moves this Queſtion: But the meer Right, and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſomneſs, and vaſt unweildyneſs of theſe Commiſſions of Appeal: And for that whatever ſhall be the chance iſſue of this fortuitous Commiſſion, It may be undone by virtue of a prohibition out of the Kings Bench, which as well reverſeth ſentences after they are pronounced for that the matter belonged not to that forum, as it doth inhibit their procedure where it comes in time. To prove that matrimonial Cauſes are not of Eccleſiaſtical Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance I ſhall now proceed. Matrimony is as old as the World, and it will be hard in the ſearch of Hiſtory to find a time when any People was without that inſtitution lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then without Government; Marriages and Familys were before Government, but Governments every where in all Ages injoyn'd them diſhoner'd and diſgrac't Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and concubinat honor'd Chaſtity, and made Whores infamous. Marriage was no invention of Prieſt craft, as a prophane immoral man in Leud Rhime dare pronounce
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49899:14"/>
Poet, he ought not to be called that title which might belong to his inventing faculty he hath forfeited by his impiety, and immorality Poets were the antient Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues and Teachers of manners, he that is a Poet ought to know,
<q>
                  <l>Quid deceat quid non quo virtus quo ferat Error
<bibl>
                        <hi>Hor. Art.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
                  <l>Scribendi rectè, ſapere eſt &amp; principium &amp; fons.
<bibl>Poet.</bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This Mans owes all his eſteem to the Debaucherys of the Age; If the People ſhould recover their Wits which they have loſt with their manners they would uſe him, as the People of <hi>Athens</hi> did <hi>Dioniſius</hi> at the <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick</hi> Games for his wicked Poem, tho they at firſt were taken with the compoſition. It is no matter who ſuch a man diſgraceth, that publickly blaſphemes, reviles Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, and the Laws of Chaſtity; ſuch publick impudence qualifies him to ſay or write whatever is falſe, whatever is evil; he is bad enough to diſgrace the worſt of Men, and the worſt of Cauſes.</p>
            <p>Marriages were every where injoyn'd by Governments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and promoted, aſſiſted and conducted by Laws and Acts of ſtate, and the liberty of marriage had more or leſs reſtraint, as the Laws of ſeveral Nations did appoint. The Greeks, Romans and Germans forbid polygamy, But the Eaſterlings allow'd it. The Romans made thoſe marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages unlawful, which the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> made ſo, and alſo forbid other marriages that were not by the <hi>Moſaical Law</hi> prohibited, as for Example. The marriage of the Uncle and Neice which the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> doth not forbid, tho it forbid's the Nephew to marry his Aunt or Uncles Wife:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49899:15"/>
But the Aſiatick's us'd a licence of polygamy, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all marriages but thoſe that the Roman Law call's <hi>Nuptiae nefariae</hi> i. e Between Parents and Children and even ſuch marriages were ſometimes committed amongſt them. But cauſes of marriages were alwayes, and every where judged by the ordinary Courts of Judicature, and as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contract's were judged: The Law's of mariage were not dictated by the Prieſts but enacted by the Legislators neither did ever any <hi>forum</hi> belong to the Prieſt hood in that capacity before Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>It was not the office of the Prieſt's of the pagan Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to inſtruct the People in moral's, or to guide their Conſciences by the rules of virtue; for this they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to their Phyloſophers and Poets: paganiſme was a Religion divided and abſtracted from morality; That did neither teach it, nor enforce it, their Prieſt's were Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, Conjurers and Sooth Sayers, and no office did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them that referd to the ſtate, except in difficult affaires of ſtate, to ſerve a turn ſometimes by their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Augury's, and by their Arts of Divination.</p>
            <p>The Laws of Marriage given to the Jews were the Laws of God, as all their other Laws were, and adminiſtred as all their otheir Laws were adminiſtred, and not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to a Judicature of Prieſts: Their Laws tho given by God did oblidge only the People of the Jews; and loſt all effect as Laws with the diſſolution of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Religion contains no inſtitutions, that can properly be called Laws, except the Inſtitution of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49899:15"/>
of the Supper of our Lord, and Baptiſme. But it gives rules and precepts of an Excellent morality, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires greater degrees of Virtues to be exerciſed: A great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Chaſtity, Mercy, Goodneſs and Temperance than the Moſaical Law requir'd in the inſtances therein defin'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd under penalties and a civil Sention.</p>
            <p>By and in analogy to the general Inſtitutions and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of our Saviour, the Chriſtians were to govern them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not determined by any definitive Law, and as in the State of nature the conduct of theſe Virtues, was by the meaſures of a Wiſe Man, <hi>prout vir prudens definiverit</hi> to Chriſtians, the General rule of all their actions is, <hi>prout vir Chriſtianus definiverit.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtians, though they did not take themſelves to be bound to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they took themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd not to do leſs than that Law requir'd, but to proceed to perfection.</p>
            <p>The Gentile Chriſtians by the Councel held at <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> Apoſt. 15.28. Were enjoyn'd amongſt other things <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> in his Book <hi>de jure Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Secundum Hebraeos,</hi> interprets to forbid all thoſe Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, that were Interdicted to the <hi>Jews.</hi> He that will take the pains to conſult him will be very well pleaſed and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed with his noble interpretation of that text.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Church did after proceed further in ſeveral prohibitions of marriages, for the better ſecurity of the Virtue of Chaſtity, which was in the firſt Ages the Honor and Glory of the Chriſtian Church, they highly commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49899:16"/>
Caelebate diſgrac't Second marriages (though they could not forbid them) and prohibited ſometime, that they ſhould not be honor'd with the preſence of a Prieſt when celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vides Sacratas Virgines,</l>
               <l>miraris intactas anus,</l>
               <l>primi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſt damnum Tori</l>
               <l>Ignis ſecundi neſcias. prudentius ad L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur.</l>
               <l>hoc eſt monile Eccleſiae</l>
               <l>his illa gemmis colitur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Even for Adultery, they would not allow it commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble immediatly to diſſolve the marriage, but to live in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the Womans Repentance.</p>
            <p>When the Governments became Chriſtian they became conformable to her rule and honor'd her more pure inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and were governed by them, for that marriages was made a Symbol of the Vnion between Chriſt and his Church, and the exerciſe and conduct of a glorious Chriſtian Virtue was principally concerned in the limitation of marriages: The declaring in what degrees and in what circumſtances perſons might marry, or not marry, was ſubmitted to the directions of the Guides of the Church.</p>
            <p>And ſo in all Chriſtian Governments, a marriage, that was made well in fact according to the order of the ſecular Law, was lawfully to be undone if the Church judg'd the perſons not fit to come together in marriage for any reaſons of great undecence or offence againſt the Chriſtian Virtue of Chaſtity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49899:16"/>But this Power and Authority ſo duly lodg'd in the guides of our Religion, for that it was to the purpoſe to inſtruct and guide Chriſtians, how to behave themſelves in one of the principal Virtues of their Religion, was inſufferably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd after the Papal Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>The Pontificial and Canon Law multiplied reſtraints up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on marriages to inconvenience, and relaxed them for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and the moſt inceſtuous marriages they made lawfull at a great price. The Roman Prieſts deſpiſe marriage, and make it more profane than Fornication, nay then Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſelf. And yet they have turn'd marriage in a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and have ty'd the <hi>Vinculum Matrimonii</hi> harder upon the laity than our Saviour left it. The <hi>Vinculum Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nii,</hi> they declare and determine to continue, when the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is divorced for Adultery. Though our Saviour allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Adultery a good cauſe of Divorce, for amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> there was no other Divorce, but what did utterly reſcind the Marriage.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Vaughan</hi> was miſtaken when he calls this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce an impeachment of the marriage, but this miſtake he run into, to ſupport his Opinion, that the Statutes of <hi>H.</hi> 8. hereafter conſidered left ſome marriages to be impeached by the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, and his other opinion he grounds upon this <hi>Hipotheſis</hi> vizt. that Queſtions of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages belong ſtill to the <hi>Curia Chriſtianitatis,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Statutes of <hi>H.</hi> 8. which opinion of his will appear a miſtake by what we have hereafter to ſay. For the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church hath not done ſo well with us in the caſe of an Adultereſs wife: But in this if in any thing they are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49899:17"/>
               <hi>iniquiores in Matrimonium</hi> which hath been laid to their charg; for they will not allow the marriage for this cauſe to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached. But have bound heavy burthens upon the ſtate of marriage, to tempt the Laity to decline it, whilſt they diſdain it.</p>
            <p>In this we complain of that Church, that they departed from the primitive Church, in making that neceſſary to all Men; which the firſt Chriſtians only commended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Liberty of Choice to the good and virtuous, and bind them to ſuſtain the Calamity of a continuing Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in all Caſes; whether the Man can or cannot ſuſtain the want of a Wife, and when the womans amendment is deſperate as well as when hopeful. By this means, the condition of the Man was made very afflictive and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſs. And without relief or recompence in the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of mind, which accrues from the generous and worthy Reſolutions proceeding from an Extraordinary virtue: A remedy againſt this Evil, the Reformation hath attempted but could never yet effect.</p>
            <p>But againſt the miſchiefs of their arbitrary Reſtraints of commendable Marriages: It is provided by our ſtatute Laws which we ſhall now conſider, and from thence it will appear that the Queſtion of the lawfulneſs of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, for the Reaſons aforementioned, divided from the ſecular Courts is now conſolidated with the Queſtion of Fact which was never remov'd from the civil Judicature. As alſo for remedy againſt the laviſh uſe of the diſpenſatory Powers, aſſum'd by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church with forbidden, and unlawful marriages for this purpoſe. It was enacted and declared 25. U. 8. Cap. 22. That theſe marriages following of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49899:17"/>
which ſome are nefarious, and others accounted more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable inceſtuous, that is to ſay
<q>
                  <l>Of the Son to the Mother</l>
                  <l>Of the Son to the Step-mother</l>
                  <l>Of the Brother to the Siſter</l>
                  <l>Of the Father to his Sons Daughter</l>
                  <l>Of the Father to his Daughters Daughter</l>
                  <l>Of the Son to his Fathers Daughter born by the Step-mother</l>
                  <l>Of the Son to his Aunt his Fathers or Mothers Siſter</l>
                  <l>Of the Son to his Unkles Wife</l>
                  <l>Of the Father to his Sons Wife</l>
                  <l>Of the Brother to his Brothers Wife</l>
                  <l>Of a man to his Wives Sons Daughter</l>
                  <l>Of a Man to his Wives Daughters Daughter</l>
                  <l>Of a Man to his Wives Siſter.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Are plainly prohibited by Gods Law, and that no man can diſpenſe with Gods Law, and that a ſeparation be in ſuch marriages be definitive Sentence in the Spiritual Courts of the Kingdom, without prohibition from, or appeal to <hi>Rome,</hi> of ſuch marriages.</p>
            <p>By this Act marriages did become of lay Cognizance, faith Sir <hi>John Vaughan R.</hi> 214. for the Kings Court were requir'd by this Law by the Kings writ of <hi>Mandamus,</hi> to enjoyn the Eccleſiaſtical Courts to treat ſuch unlawful Perſons, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing marriage, as inceſtuous Perſons. But whether this ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made marriages of lay Cognizance, I will not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, for the ſtatute that direct to whom adminiſtration ſhall be committed, doth not take the matter of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Common Law Courts, neither do the writs of our Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> which iſſue to the Biſhops, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49899:18"/>
them to aſſail an Excommunicant give the power of the Keys to the Secular Courts.</p>
            <p>There was nothing by this Act of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. done to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the power of the Church in declaring what other marriages were unlawfull. This Act only reſtrained the Popes power of diſpenſing with ſuch unlawful marriages, and gave Authority to the Kings Court, to injoyn and command the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, to diſſolve ſuch marriages by their definitive Sentence, without regard had to the prohibition from, or Appeal to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the ſtatute 28. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 7. the former Act of 25. is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, but the power of the Papal diſpenſation in ſuch mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages is condemned; the ſaid marriages are recited again, and declared to be prohibited by Gods Law only, with theſe differences, that in the prohibition of the Sons marrying the Step-mother, of marrying the Unckles Wife of the Father, marrying his Sons Wife of the Brother, marrying the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Wife is added, carnally known by the Father, Unckle, Son, Brother reſpectively, and in the prohibition to marry the Wives Daughter or her Sons Daughter, or her Daughters is added, having Carnal Knowledg of his Wife.</p>
            <p>And with this further addition, That if any man carnal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know any woman, all perſons in any degree of conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or affinity of the perſons ſo offending, ſhall be adjudged to be within the ſaid prohibitions, in like manner, as if the parties ſo marrying one another had been marryed: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, if a man carnally know a Woman not marrying her, he is prohibited to marry her daughter or daughters daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In all other clauſes this Act, and the former Act of 25 are <hi>Verbatim</hi> the ſame, and this Act is in force. Sir <hi>John Vaughan</hi> ſays, <hi>Rep.</hi> 215. that theſe degrees were the ſecond time made of Lay Cognizance. In this Act diſpenſations for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49899:18"/>
ſuch marriages are prohibited: And for that this Act did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare theſe marriages to be prohibited by Gods Law, they were declared and made indispenſably unlawful, null &amp; void, and that they could not be ligitimated by the Papal Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And thereby the Common Law Courts had a power given them to iſſue out the Kings writ of mandamus, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them to diſſolve ſuch Marriages by their definitive ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>But the Arbitrary power of that Church in defining the lawfulneſs of marriages, yet remained in full force and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>impeached, which was an Authority very much abus'd by unreaſonable reſtraints of the freedom of marriage, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of this, there was a proviſion made by 28. <hi>H.</hi> 8. C. 16. That all marriages made before the 3d day of Nov. 26. <hi>H.</hi> 8. whereof there is no divorce had by the Eccleſiaſtical Laws of the Realm, and which be not prohibited by Gods Law limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and declared in the Act made this preſent Parliament, for Eſtabliſhing the King's Succeſſion or otherwiſe by holy Scriptures, ſhall be lawfull and effectual by Authority of this preſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>This Law went in Confirmation but to ſome few marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, before that time made and not reſcinded by divorce thus forbidden by the Canons of the Church, but yet left the power of the Church unabated ſtill, in declaring marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages unlawful, other than are by the Law in <hi>Leviticus</hi> prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, in all marriages, but thoſe within that time made and not divorced.</p>
            <p>But by the ſtatute of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. Cap. 34. a full and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat remedy is provided againſt the unreaſonable aſſumings of the Canon Law, to reſtrain the Liberty of marriage for ſlight and phantaſtical motives and inducements, by which the Virtue of Chaſtity was not materially promoted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49899:19"/>By this act it was declared, <hi>That all perſons lawfull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract marriages, that be not prohibited by Gods Law to marry; And it is thereby enacted, That no prohibition or reſervation Gods Law Except, ſhall trouble or impeach any marriage without the Levitical degrees, And that no Perſon of what Eſtate, degree or Condition whatſoever he or ſhe be; ſhall after the ſaid firſt day of the month of July aforeſaid, be admitted in any ſpiritual Courts within the Kings Realm, or any by Graces other Lands and Dominions to any proceſs, plea or allegation contrary to this Act,</hi> ſome part of this as to precontracts was repeal'd by <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. and the reſidue was repeal'd by 1. 2. <hi>P.</hi> m. but it is revived 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Cap. 2. and now in full force.</p>
            <p>Note, That the words by <hi>Gods Law,</hi> and the words or <hi>otherwiſe by Holy Scripture</hi> in theſe two laſt mentioned Acts, refer both to the Laws about marriages in <hi>Leviticus.</hi> But for that beſides the caſes expreſly limited and declared in that Law, other marriages within a parity of reaſon by the true ſenſe of that Law, (which is the Law and the Scripture) might be intended prohibited, and therefore prohibited by that Law, it is added <hi>or otherwiſe in holy Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides that of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> there is no part of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if that prohibits or makes unlawfull any marriage. Chriſt made no Law about the Lawfulneſs of marriages, but confirm'd thoſe which the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> had allowed, againſt the abuſe of the liberty of divorcing, permitted to the <hi>Jews</hi> by the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the aforementioned ſtatute, that Law in <hi>Leviticus</hi> is made the ſtatute Law of <hi>England,</hi> it is become of Lay Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance, and however the Divines may gloſs upon the text, our Judges have the Authority of a Legal and binding inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of that part of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Our Judges at Common Law, are as competent to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret this Law in <hi>Leviticus</hi> as any Divines, and need not want
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49899:19"/>
any Learning that is neceſſary for expounding thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that they have ſenſes exerciſed to make right and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting interpretations of Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In omnibus legibus etiam maximè odioſis quales ſunt quae pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam irrogant receptum eſt, vbi eadem eſt ratio jus idem valeat. In benignioribus autem legibus etiam à paribus ad paria procedit interpretatio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Courts may follow the <hi>Karaej,</hi> who interpret it to caſes of parity of reaſon, or the <hi>Talmudiſts</hi> which ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the enumerated Caſes of the Law, or follow their own opinion different from them both.</p>
            <p>The words (Gods Law excepted) cannot prejudice the Authority of our Judges in this matter, tho they are inſiſted on by ſome; as if the whole Canon of the Scripture was to be conſulted in this matter, and the whole Science of The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology muſt be underſtood before we can come to a Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, what marriages are forbidden by Gods Law in the holy Scriptures</p>
            <p>To leave the Eccleſiaſtical Courts an Authority to undo any marriage upon a pretence, that they are the beſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of Gods Law; To give them leave to pretend the Law of God for the unlawfulneſs of any marriage, other then what is expreſly or literally forbidden, or interpretatively, or upon conſtruction in the Law of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> would make the Law illuſory and fruſtraneous: Eſpecially if they are left Judges of the matters, for then they can and will to be ſure allow their own pretences and reaſons, and no prohibition ought to iſſue to the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, or elſe they not bound to obey, and they have a ready anſwer in caſe of a prohibition, to the Kings Bench <hi>(vizt.)</hi> that Doctors differ upon the Law, this ſtated I proceed and conclude.</p>
            <p>The Law of <hi>Leviticus</hi> is the only Law, that reſtrains the liberty of marriage in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49899:20"/>The Law of <hi>Leviticus</hi> is become part of our ſtatute Law, as much as it would have been, if the matter thereof had been tranſcribed into the Act of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. without reference to the text; or as if a Law of <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Athens</hi> had been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by Authority of our Parliament to be the Rule, and meaſure in the Government of any Affair.</p>
            <p>But the Law of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. the definitive Authority of the Church of what marriages are lawful is taken away.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of this Law the Eccleſiaſtical Courts can never bring into queſtion any marriage, for any pretence for their Canon, that the Perſons are not lawful</p>
            <p>That the Queſtion conſequently of the legitimateneſs of marriages, is reſtor'd to the Judgment of the civil and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Courts.</p>
            <p>In that this Law of <hi>Leviticus</hi> by our Law, is called the Law of God (tho it is not truly ſo to us) it muſt have ſuch Authority as a Law of God ought to have, and we are to conclude, that our Law-makers intended it ſhould have the like Effect, as a Law of God by ſtyling it ſo.</p>
            <p>As any matter that is called, and rated a <hi>Commune Nocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum</hi> or nuſance in any ſtatute Law, is for that it is ſo called in any Law, indiſpenſable by a <hi>Non Obſtante.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the Laws of God, which prohibit any thing to be done from that abſolute Right and Dominion, that God hath over us; makes all Acts contrary to the prohibition ſinful and impious, without all Effect null and void; It is not ſo in human Laws, except they add to the words of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, words that irritate.</p>
            <p>A Marriage may be forbidden by human Laws, that do not annul the marriage when made of ſuch Laws; there are many, <hi>Ulpian</hi> calls them <hi>Leges imperfectae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that the Law, abovementioned hath made the Law of God to the Jews of prohibition of marriages the Law of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49899:20"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> But hath not made the particular Laws of God, for diſpenſation or allowance of marriages (as between the Heireis and the next of Kin: And the younger Brothers marrying the relict of the Elder Brother dying without iſſue, which were alſo the Laws of <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Sparta.</hi>) the Law of our Land: Such marriages are not allowable by our Law, but ſtand interdicted by the general prohibition of that Law, which is only made the Law of <hi>England</hi> under the notion of the Law of God.</p>
            <p>We further therefore conclude, that a marriage with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe prohibited degrees is no marriage.</p>
            <p>Perſons contracting marriage within theſe degrees are no more marry'd then two women or two men can be marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: A moral faculty to a moral Act is as neceſſary, as a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ability to the producing a natural Act.</p>
            <p>It was comprehended in the Queſtion, whether a marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was had in fact at common Law? whether it was a man marryed to a woman, whether both perſons were of ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to make the contract? whether either of them precontra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or before that, marryed? for the Perſon precontracted or before marry'd had no power left over him or herſelf: Whether if by force or <hi>Dolus malus</hi> the marriage wanted conſent? for then it was likewiſe no marriage: All theſe matters come into Iſſue upon the Queſtion marry'd or not marry'd, and the truth of theſe matters are underſtood by proof or inſpection as all other things of like nature are prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and no religious Notices are requiſite to inſtruct the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry upon a Trial thereof had; and therefore was never of right proper for an Eccleſiaſtical Court. And now in like manner, if the Perſons be not lawful, the marriage for that reaſon is null, and the Queſtion is a Queſtion of Fact now <hi>(vizt.)</hi> whether of kin or how a kin? not of Law <hi>(vizt.)</hi> whether Perſons ſo a kin may marry an utter Diſability in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49899:21"/>
the Perſons diſabled, hinders the marriage to proceed, and there is now no Judgment of Diſcretion left to the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Courts.</p>
            <p>The common Law Courts had Knowledge of the Queſtion whether marriage or not marriage, this cannot be denyed or brought in queſtion with any colour or ſhadow of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. A man need not go into the Eccleſiaſtical Court to prove his marriage before he can ſue for that Eſtate, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his wife as he muſt to prove a will before he can ſue as Executor, and any man may directly declare upon a right acquired to him by marriage of his Wife.</p>
            <p>The Fact and Law in the caſe of marriages is now the ſame, and the diſtinction of marriage, and Legal marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is taken away.</p>
            <p>The queſtion is now ſingle, whether marriage or not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and therefore cannot be divided into two cognizances: And this belongs ſolely to the temporal Courts, for that the Eccleſiaſtical Court cannot allow of what the temporal Law hath declared to be contrary to the Law of God. Nor can they have conuſance of a ſtatute Law, they cannot impeach any marriage that our Statute ſaith ſhall not be impeached; and whether it ought to be impeached or no, whether within the Statute or no, they are by no means to judge. Our Judges iſſue out writs of mandamus to the Eccleſiaſtical Courts, to require them to ſeparate and puniſh Perſons, making marriages by our Law inceſtuous and void; as well as we prohibit them, if they diſquiet any marriage by our Law made lawful in which our Judges interpret, declare and reſolve uncontrolably: The Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Courts can neither bind nor looſe judicially, and therefore can have no judicial Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49899:21"/>And therefore I conceive the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Courts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed their Juriſdictions, as it is now reſtrain'd in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of theſe <hi>Statutes,</hi> if they bring any <hi>Marriage</hi> into queſtion in that Court; and ought to be Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſince, that the queſtion of Right and Law (which was proper for them, when they gave the Rule of the Lawfulneſs and unlawfulneſs of the Degrees) is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a queſtion of Fact, and is Cognoſcible in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law-Courts.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Marriage</hi> Try'd at Law, is not controllable by the Authority of the <hi>Curia Christianitatis:</hi> And where there hath been a Tryal at Law in affirmation of a <hi>Marriage,</hi> the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Courts interpoſings for that reaſon the rather ought to be Prohibited.</p>
            <p>By the aforementioned Laws, all <hi>Marriages</hi> made within the Levitical degrees are <hi>ipſo jure null,</hi> and void and indiſpenſable by any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Authority: And <hi>Marriages</hi> without the Levitical Degrees by the <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> Courts, are not Impeachable. No proceſs Plea, or Allegation is to be allowed in any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Court, to trouble or impeach ſuch <hi>Marriages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore it is no Objection, or Argument, that the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Courts, notwithſtanding have ſtill Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of Matrimonial Cauſes. For that Conſultations are granted upon Prohibitions, when the <hi>Marriage</hi> is made between Perſons not Lawful, and within the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical Degrees. For in ſuch caſes, thoſe Courts have no Power of Judgment or Diſcretion. They do not Annul ſuch <hi>Marriages</hi> by their definitive Sentence: For they are (by our Law) no <hi>Marriages,</hi> and void, and made <hi>null</hi> to their Hands; and whether they will or no. A Conſultation in ſuch Cauſes, is but a ſofter word for an Injunction or Mandat to Separate the Perſons, and Puniſh them by the Cenſures of the Church, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49899:22"/>
which if they do not do upon a Conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they will be peremptorily Enjoyn'd to do by the Authority of the <hi>King</hi>'s Court.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Vaughan,</hi> would have Matrimonial Cauſes to be ſtill of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Cognizance, <hi>read pag.</hi> 320.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> For that ſome <hi>Marriages</hi> are allowed to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful by <hi>God</hi>'s Law, which are not within the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Degrees: And from thence would infer, That there remains a Judgment and Authority in the <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> Courts in Matrimonial Cauſes; and that the definitive Authority of the <hi>Church of Marriages</hi> Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or unlawful, is not extinguiſhed by the aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Statutes.</p>
            <p>His inſtances to prove this, are theſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> A <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi> made with a Perſon Precontracted, or with a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon naturally Impotent: Theſe <hi>Marriages</hi> he ſaith, are againſt <hi>God</hi>'s Law; yet they are not <hi>Marriages</hi> within the Levitical Degrees.</p>
            <p>But all the World hath taken ſuch <hi>Marriages</hi> to be no <hi>Marriages;</hi> and therefore not unlawful <hi>Marriages:</hi> And the matter of impotency or percontract, makes a <hi>Marriage</hi> none in fact, and enquirable in an Iſſue at Common-Law, whether <hi>Married</hi> or not <hi>Married.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Second</hi> Reaſon is, For that <hi>Canons</hi> may be made by the Authority of the <hi>Church,</hi> to make other <hi>Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages,</hi> which are not within the Levitical Degrees, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful. A Lawful <hi>Canon</hi> is the Law of the Kingdom, as well as an Act of Parliament. This is a great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox indeed, that <hi>Canons</hi> are Laws, that they can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul Laws. That a <hi>Parliament</hi> can give away the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Authority, and impower any Synod or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, to Abrogate their Laws.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He makes an Arbitrary diſtinction between a <hi>Marriage</hi> within the Levitical Degrees, and a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49899:22"/>
within the Levitical Prohibition: And would have more <hi>Marriages</hi> within the Degrees, than are the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages</hi> Prohibited; and conſequently ſome Matrimonial Cauſes ſtill remaining to the Judgment of the <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> Courts.</p>
            <p>And this he proves from an Inſtance of the Wives Siſter, which is within the Degrees, he ſaith, but not Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in all caſes, he thinks, becauſe it is Prohibited to <hi>Marry</hi> her, during his Wives Life, but doubted if Lawful after her Death.</p>
            <p>But this doubt is put to an end, by 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. as is before recited, which declares it to be Prohibited by <hi>God</hi>'s Law, and indiſpenſable, and the Perſons to be Separated.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſonings of a great Man, as Sir <hi>John Vaug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han</hi> truly was, are a remarkable inſtance, how tempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble great Men are to aſſume, ſpeak things <hi>Gratis,</hi> and affect to be <hi>ſuper</hi>-fine, Heterodox, and Sceptical.</p>
            <p>True it is, after this reſtraint of <hi>Marriage</hi> limited by our Laws, The <hi>Church</hi> by her <hi>Canons</hi> may uſe her Authority to bring into diſlike, diſcommend, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade other <hi>Marriages</hi> that are by our Law allowed, and are not to be Impeach'd by the <hi>Eccleſiastical</hi> Courts; and by this means <hi>Marriages</hi> ſo diſſwaded, may at length be brought into diſreputation, and general diſlike; and come in time to be made unlawful. But the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of ſuch <hi>Canons</hi> cannot be enjoyn'd under the <hi>incurring</hi> of <hi>Church</hi>-Cenſures, and by a judical coercion of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Authority: to affect which ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, belongs to the Law and Civil Authority. <hi>Infamiae quoque irrogatio pars eſt Gladii,</hi> ſaith <hi>Grotius,</hi> in his Book <hi>de jure Summarum poteſtatum circa ſacra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But moſt commendable it is to lay Reſtraints upon our ſelves for the ſake of Virtue, where the Laws have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49899:23"/>
left us at liberty. In the time when the <hi>Christians</hi> obſerved <hi>Moſes</hi> Law; that of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> was veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in their Practiſes;
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
They obey the Laws, and in their Lives are better than the Laws require: And if any Man will, for the regard to the virtue of Chaſtity, abſtain from a <hi>Marriage</hi> of a <hi>Coſin German,</hi> or any other near of Kin to him; and therefore forgoe any advantage; it ought to be imputed to him, as a worthy inſtance of Virtue, and very Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable: But <hi>God</hi> hath made no poſitive Law to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit them. Our Laws have not forbidden them; and Nature hath yet made no Law to prohibit and reſtrain them: For Nature, as well as Polities, makes Laws up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Emergent Miſchiefs, and great Inconveniencies, that do ariſe from the uſe of Natural Liberty, were the firſt permiſſion was innocent; but whatever is not the beſt, and whatever is not very convenient, is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd as a Law under the ſanction of an evil Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>The Laws of Nature are the directions of Reaſon for avoiding Miſchief, or obtaining ſome important Good to the generality of Mankind; and direct us where Laws do not command. <hi>Latius patet officiorum quam Juris re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula. Quod non vetat lex hoc vetat fieri pudor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he that is not a Law to himſelf from his ſlow Apprehenſion, and dull Capacity, is Governed only by Penalty, and the ſharp Reſtraints of Law. The Law of Nature is no more to be meaſured by the underſtandings and Conſciences of ſome Men, than it is to be defin'd by the propenſions and actings of beaſts.</p>
            <p>Neither are the Laws of Nature to be numbred, for they are as many as the various Applications of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the emergent Caſes; and there is no end of her legiſlative Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49899:23"/>Men of refined Senſes do ſooneſt apprehend theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies, which render things by the the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of humane Nature or Reaſon unlawful; and by their Authority firſt, and after that, by the concurrent Senſe of inferiour Men, that at length reflect, they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of great inconvenience and miſchief: Become at length deteſtable, and in proceſs of time an averſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and loathing is begot in the loweſt order of Men to tranſgreſs them. Whatſoever, by a general Opinion, is made infamous, from the regard that every Man hath to his own Eſteem by Nature, he is oblig'd to ſhun and avoid. And if any thing to which we are not under an obligation to obſerve from a declared Will of God, be thus, by general Opinion, rendred infamous; we are bound by the Law of Modeſty to refrain from it, who is a ſevere Avenger of any Tranſgreſſion committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Her: There is not a more oppreſſive and afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Paſſion, than that of ſhame and dejection of Mind; the moſt bitter ingredient in remorſe of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Nature did not make all her Laws at firſt.</p>
            <p>This the <hi>Jews</hi> expreſs inartificially, when they ſay, That <hi>God</hi> gave <hi>Adam</hi> a Law in the Beginning, againſt Brothers <hi>Marrying</hi> their Siſters; but <hi>God</hi> diſpens'd with it for the Peopling of the World, and deriving all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from one Stock.</p>
            <p>Nothing becomes a Law of <hi>God</hi> in our Nature and Conſciences, before it is behoof-ful to have it obſerved, and hurtful to have it neglected. It was no more a Law to <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sons, not to <hi>Marry</hi> their Siſters, for the preventing early Luſt and diſorder in Families, than it was a Law to <hi>Adam, not to Steal;</hi> or to <hi>Eve, not to commit Adultery:</hi> When there was no Lord, or Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the World but himſelf; and no Man beſides <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:49899:24"/>For that a matter at ſome time may be Lawful; and for avoiding miſchief and inconveniency, may, in after time, become unlawful and prohibited: Will aſſoil that doubt how it comes about, That ſeveral of the <hi>Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages</hi> prohibited in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> were uſed by the beſt of Men, whoſe Story is Recorded by <hi>Moſes</hi> before the Law: As <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Marrying <hi>Sarah</hi> his Siſter by the Father: <hi>Amram, Moſes</hi> his Father Marrying <hi>Jochebed,</hi> his Fathers Siſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law was added, becauſe of Tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of ſuch <hi>Marriages</hi> at that time, by no Law forbidden, Mankind had corrupted themſelves: It was fit therefore, that by a Law, a Reſtraint ſhould be made of thoſe Licences, that in the whole complicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, had depraved humane Nature with inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Luſt, and engaged them more frequently in thoſe deſires, which became (by the permiſſion of Perſons of the neareſt Kindred of every days Converſation, to be a Lawful Object of Love, and an allowed perſon for <hi>Marriage</hi>) moſt hurtful by their importunity.</p>
            <p>So great a Miſchief this permiſſion had wrought, and ſuch a Corruption, if manners in the <hi>Canaanites</hi> that they had proceeded from the inceſtuous and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient <hi>Marriages</hi> upon the Reaſon aforeſaid, to nefarious Mixtures; nay, to mingle with Beaſts, and to invert the Order of Nature: And for theſe Abominations they came to be deſtroy'd, the Land was defiled, and was now to Vomit forth the Inhabitants, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 27. There needs not that Niceneſs that great Criticks have uſed to reſtrain the word Abominations, to nefarious and unnatural Mixtures: Who think it not Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable, that the term <hi>Abominations, Levit.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 27. be applyed to the inceſtuous <hi>Marriages</hi> at that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to the <hi>Jews.</hi> But even theſe Marriages, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49899:24"/>
of the Corruption and Debauchery of manners they had occaſion; and thoſe more horrid Abominations that followed in Conſequence of theſe Marriages. I think, for theſe Reaſons, even theſe Marriages were now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Abominable.</p>
            <p>Moſt neceſſary it is to preſerve Men in any degree good and virtuous, and uſeful to any good purpoſes: That they ſhould, in ordinary Converſation, be reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Luſt and Amours, and be enjoyn'd great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancies from thoſe impure deſires: That they ſhould not every where, where-ever they go, find an Object to ſollicit them. That the innocent Friendſhip of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and Kindreds, ſhould be preſerved pure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, which Miniſters the trueſt pleaſure and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Life; and by no means become an invitation to Luſt, that is apt to waſt and utterly Deſtroy them. That Families ſhould not be inceſſantly haunted, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, and curſed by Luſt, and Rage two Devils that are never divided, and are inſeparable aſſociates. By permiſſion of Marriages, in ſuch degrees, Families are apt to be turn'd into Styes of unclean Beaſts. And Men to be engag'd and plung'd in ſuch deſires, and wholly Govern'd by them, ſo as to be made <hi>Mentulae lacinia as petronius Arbiter</hi> ſharply pronounc'd of the Sparks of that Age. And a great part of mankind eaſily turn'd into a ſalacious ſort of Virmin, good for nothing (if for that) but to propagate their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthyneſs fit to be deſtroyed by divine Vengeance, for recovering the humane Nature from Perdition.</p>
            <p>I have but one thing more to obſerve about this Law, which will make out the Rationale of it, which ſome great Men have thought inexplicable: and that is the admirable Wiſdom, and Divinity in the Structure of it.</p>
            <p>That which this Law deſigns to promote, is made
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49899:25"/>
the inducement of the Law. But this which becomes the inducement, the Law it ſelf inculcates and teacheth: The Law it ſelf introduceth ſuch an underſtanding in the Minds of the people, as makes the things that it forbids by the very propounding of them, fit for aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. It at once improves natural Modeſty, and ſets a Fence about it, by ſtrict prohibitions and penalties. For it calls thoſe Enjoyments the <hi>Nakedneſs</hi> of the Man and Woman, <hi>i. e.</hi> their <hi>Shame;</hi> and ſo makes them the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the <hi>Natural pudor.</hi> It teacheth us to reverence our Relations: And out of reſpect and good manners, we are not to caſt our Thoughts no more than our Eyes upon thoſe Enjoyments which they are taught by this Law to Bluſh at, if ſeen and detected. Theſe are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacies that we muſt not enter with our Thoughts. Acts that are to be done alone, and will admit no partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pants; no not in Succeſſion, if we value our ſelves (for we ought to maintain a reſpect to our ſelves, for the ſupporting the order of the World, and a reverence is therefore due to our inferiours, <hi>Maxima etiam pueris de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur reverentia</hi>) or reſpect thoſe Relatives which we ought to reverence: For this Law in the ſence of it inſtructs us, that they are leſſen'd when remembred by them. By this Law, and the frame of it, all obſcene talk and filthy communication is more than interdicted; for thoſe that are inſtructed by this Law, and are under the reaſon of it, muſt even abhor ſuch Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as they do expoſing their own Nakedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> Thus I have performed your deſires, as I could in that ſhortneſs of time you allowed me: What is done in obedience to your Command, cannot fail of your Acceptance.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
